<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<item name="conditions">

    <condition name="Bleed" >
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Take damage at beginning of turn<br/>
    	    &#8226; Stopped by DC 15 Heal check or magical healing<br/>
    	    &#8226; Do not stack unless they deal different kinds of damage<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A creature that is taking bleed damage takes the listed amount of damage at the beginning of its turn. Bleeding can be stopped by a DC 15 Heal 
            check or through the application of any spell that cures hit point damage (even if the bleed is ability damage). Some bleed effects cause ability 
            damage or even ability drain. Bleed effects do not stack with each other unless they deal different kinds of damage. When two or more bleed effects 
            deal the same kind of damage, take the worse effect. In this case, ability drain is worse than ability damage.
        </long_description>
    </condition>
    <condition name="Blinded" >
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; -2 AC<br/>
    	    &#8226; No DEX bonus to AC<br/>
    	    &#8226; -4 on most STR and DEX skills and Perception<br/>
    	    &#8226; DC 20 Acrobatics to move faster than half speed]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
    	    The creature cannot see. It takes a –2 penalty to Armor Class, loses its Dexterity bonus to AC (if any), and takes a –4 penalty on most Strength- 
    	    and Dexterity-based skill checks and on opposed Perception skill checks. All checks and activities that rely on vision (such as reading and 
    	    Perception checks based on sight) automatically fail. All opponents are considered to have total concealment (50% miss chance) against the blinded 
    	    character. Blind creatures must make a DC 10 Acrobatics skill check to move faster than half speed. Creatures that fail this check fall prone. 
    	    Characters who remain blinded for a long time grow accustomed to these drawbacks and can overcome some of them.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="ac" value="-2" />
        <mod type="dex_ac" value="0" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Confused">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Treat all creatures as enemies<br/>
    	    &#8226; Roll to see happens on turn<br/>
    	    &#8226; 01-25 Act Normally<br/>
    	    &#8226; 26-50 Do nothing<br/>
    	    &#8226; 51-75 Deal 1d8 + Str mod damage to self<br/>
    	    &#8226; 76-100 Attack nearest creature<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A confused creature is mentally befuddled and cannot act normally. A confused creature cannot tell the difference between ally and foe, treating 
            all creatures as enemies. Allies wishing to cast a beneficial spell that requires a touch on a confused creature must succeed on a melee touch attack. 
            If a confused creature is attacked, it attacks the creature that last attacked it until that creature is dead or out of sight.

			Roll on the following table at the beginning of each confused subject's turn each round to see what the subject does in that round.

d%	Behavior
01–25	Act normally.
26–50	Do nothing but babble incoherently.
51–75	Deal 1d8 points of damage + Str modifier to self with item in hand.
76–100	Attack nearest creature (for this purpose, a familiar counts as part of the subject's self).
			A confused creature who can't carry out the indicated action does nothing but babble incoherently. Attackers are not at any special advantage when 
			attacking a confused creature. Any confused creature who is attacked automatically attacks its attackers on its next turn, as long as it is still 
			confused when its turn comes. Note that a confused creature will not make attacks of opportunity against anything that it is not already devoted to 
			attacking (either because of its most recent action or because it has just been attacked).
        </long_description>
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Cowering">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Take no actions<br/>
    	    &#8226; -2 to AC and lose Dex bonus<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            The character is frozen in fear and can take no actions. A cowering character takes a –2 penalty to Armor Class and loses his Dexterity bonus (if any).
        </long_description>
        <mod type="actions" value="none" />
        <mod type="ac" value="-2" />
        <mod type="dex_ac" value="0" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Dazed">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Take no actions<br/>
    	    &#8226; No penalty to AC<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            The creature is unable to act normally. A dazed creature can take no actions, but has no penalty to AC.

			A dazed condition typically lasts 1 round.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="actions" value="none" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Dazzled">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; -1 on attack rolls<br/>
    	    &#8226; -1 on sight-based Perception checks<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            The creature is unable to see well because of overstimulation of the eyes. A dazzled creature takes a –1 penalty on attack rolls and sight-based 
            Perception checks.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="hit" value="-1" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Deafened">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Can not hear<br/>
    	    &#8226; -4 on initiative<br/>
    	    &#8226; Fail Perception based on sound<br/>
    	    &#8226; -4 on opposed Perception checks<br/>
    	    &#8226; 20% spell failure on spells with verbal components<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A deafened character cannot hear. He takes a –4 penalty on initiative checks, automatically fails Perception checks based on sound, takes a –4 penalty 
            on opposed Perception checks, and has a 20% chance of spell failure when casting spells with verbal components. Characters who remain deafened for a 
            long time grow accustomed to these drawbacks and can overcome some of them.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="init" value="-4" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Disabled">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; 0 HP<br/>
    	    &#8226; Single move action or standard action<br/>
    	    &#8226; Move at half speed<br/>
    	    &#8226; Standard action deals 1 point of damage after completion<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
             A character with 0 hit points, or one who has negative hit points but has become stable and conscious, is disabled. A disabled character may take a 
             single move action or standard action each round (but not both, nor can he take full-round actions, but he can still take swift, immediate, and free 
             actions). He moves at half speed. Taking move actions doesn't risk further injury, but performing any standard action (or any other action the GM 
             deems strenuous, including some free actions such as casting a quickened spell) deals 1 point of damage after the completion of the act. Unless the 
             action increased the disabled character's hit points, he is now in negative hit points and dying.

			 A disabled character with negative hit points recovers hit points naturally if he is being helped. Otherwise, each day he can attempt a DC 10 
			 Constitution check after resting for 8 hours, to begin recovering hit points naturally. The character takes a penalty on this roll equal to his 
			 negative hit point total. Failing this check causes the character to lose 1 hit point, but this does not cause the character to become unconscious. 
			 Once a character makes this check, he continues to heal naturally and is no longer in danger of losing hit points naturally.
        </long_description>
        
        <mod type="actions" value="single" />
        <mod type="speed" value="half" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Dying">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Unconscious, no actions<br/>
    	    &#8226; DC 10 (plus negative hit point total) Con check to become stable<br/>
    	    &#8226; Lose 1 HP after failing Con check<br/>
    	    &#8226; Negative hit points equal to Con score is death<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A dying creature is unconscious and near death. Creatures that have negative hit points and have not stabilized are dying. A dying creature can take 
            no actions. On the character's next turn, after being reduced to negative hit points (but not dead), and on all subsequent turns, the character must
            make a DC 10 Constitution check to become stable. The character takes a penalty on this roll equal to his negative hit point total. A character that 
            is stable does not need to make this check. A natural 20 on this check is an automatic success. If the character fails this check, he loses 1 hit point. 
            If a dying creature has an amount of negative hit points equal to its Constitution score, it dies.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="actions" value="none" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Entangled">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Move at half speed, cannot run or charge<br/>
    	    &#8226; -2 on all attack rolls<br/>
    	    &#8226; -4 to Dex<br/>
    	    &#8226; Concentration check (DC 15 + spell level) or lose spell<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            The character is ensnared. Being entangled impedes movement, but does not entirely prevent it unless the bonds are anchored to an immobile object or 
            tethered by an opposing force. An entangled creature moves at half speed, cannot run or charge, and takes a –2 penalty on all attack rolls and a –4 
            penalty to Dexterity. An entangled character who attempts to cast a spell must make a concentration check (DC 15 + spell level) or lose the spell.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="speed" value="half" />
        <mod type="hit" value="-2" />
        <mod type="dex" value="-4" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Fascinated">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Stand still or sit quietly, take no actions<br/>
    	    &#8226; -4 on skill checks to make reactions<br/>
    	    &#8226; Any potential threat allows a new saving throw<br/>
    	    &#8226; Any obvious threat breaks spell<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A fascinated creature is entranced by a supernatural or spell effect. The creature stands or sits quietly, taking no actions other than to pay 
            attention to the fascinating effect, for as long as the effect lasts. It takes a –4 penalty on skill checks made as reactions, such as Perception 
            checks. Any potential threat, such as a hostile creature approaching, allows the fascinated creature a new saving throw against the fascinating effect. 
            Any obvious threat, such as someone drawing a weapon, casting a spell, or aiming a ranged weapon at the fascinated creature, automatically breaks the 
            effect. A fascinated creature's ally may shake it free of the spell as a standard action.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="actions" value="none" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Frightened">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Flee from source of fear<br/>
    	    &#8226; May fight if unable to flee<br/>
    	    &#8226; -2 on all attack rolls, saving throws, skill checks and ability checks<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A frightened creature flees from the source of its fear as best it can. If unable to flee, it may fight. A frightened creature takes a –2 penalty on 
            all attack rolls, saving throws, skill checks, and ability checks. A frightened creature can use special abilities, including spells, to flee; indeed, 
            the creature must use such means if they are the only way to escape.

			Frightened is like shaken, except that the creature must flee if possible. Panicked is a more extreme state of fear.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="hit" value="-2" />
        <mod type="saves" value="-2" />
        <mod type="skill_checks" value="-2" />
        <mod type="ability_checks" value="-2" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Helpless">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; 0 Dex<br/>
    	    &#8226; +4 from melee attacks<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A helpless character is paralyzed, held, bound, sleeping, unconscious, or otherwise completely at an opponent's mercy. A helpless target is treated as 
            having a Dexterity of 0 (–5 modifier). Melee attacks against a helpless target get a +4 bonus (equivalent to attacking a prone target). Ranged attacks 
            get no special bonus against helpless targets. Rogues can sneak attack helpless targets.

			As a full-round action, an enemy can use a melee weapon to deliver a coup de grace to a helpless foe. An enemy can also use a bow or crossbow, provided 
			he is adjacent to the target. The attacker automatically hits and scores a critical hit. (A rogue also gets his sneak attack damage bonus against a 
			helpless foe when delivering a coup de grace.) If the defender survives, he must make a Fortitude save (DC 10 + damage dealt) or die. Delivering a 
			coup de grace provokes attacks of opportunity.

			Creatures that are immune to critical hits do not take critical damage, nor do they need to make Fortitude saves to avoid being killed by a coup de grace.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="dex" value="-999" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Invisible">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; +2 on attack rolls against sighted opponents<br/>
    	    &#8226; Ignore opponent Dex to AC<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            Invisible creatures are visually undetectable. An invisible creature gains a +2 bonus on attack rolls against sighted opponents, and ignores its 
            opponents' Dexterity bonuses to AC (if any). See Invisibility, under Special Abilities.
        </long_description>
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Nauseated">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Unable to attack, cast spells, concentrate on spells or do anything requiring attention<br/>
    	    &#8226; Single move action<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            Creatures with the nauseated condition experience stomach distress. Nauseated creatures are unable to attack, cast spells, concentrate on spells, 
            or do anything else requiring attention. The only action such a character can take is a single move actions per turn.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="actions" value="move" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Panicked">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Drop everything held<br/>
    	    &#8226; Flee at top speed from source of fear<br/>
    	    &#8226; -2 on all saving throws, skill checks and ability checks<br/>
    	    &#8226; Cower if cornered<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A panicked creature must drop anything it holds and flee at top speed from the source of its fear, as well as any other dangers it encounters, 
            along a random path. It can't take any other actions. In addition, the creature takes a –2 penalty on all saving throws, skill checks, and ability 
            checks. If cornered, a panicked creature cowers and does not attack, typically using the total defense action in combat. A panicked creature can use 
            special abilities, including spells, to flee; indeed, the creature must use such means if they are the only way to escape.

			Panicked is a more extreme state of fear than shaken or frightened.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="saves" value="-2" />
        <mod type="skill_checks" value="-2" />
        <mod type="ability_checks" value="-2" />        
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Paralyzed">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; 0 Dex and Str<br/>
    	    &#8226; No movement or actions<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A paralyzed character is frozen in place and unable to move or act. A paralyzed character has effective Dexterity and Strength scores of 0 and is 
            helpless, but can take purely mental actions. A winged creature flying in the air at the time that it becomes paralyzed cannot flap its wings and 
            falls. A paralyzed swimmer can't swim and may drown. A creature can move through a space occupied by a paralyzed creature—ally or not. Each square 
            occupied by a paralyzed creature, however, counts as 2 squares to move through.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="dex" value="-999" />
        <mod type="str" value="-999" />
        <mod type="actions" value="none" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Pinned">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Cannot move<br/>
    	    &#8226; No Dex bonus<br/>
    	    &#8226; -4 to AC<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A pinned creature is tightly bound and can take few actions. A pinned creature cannot move and is denied its Dexterity bonus.. A pinned character 
            also takes an additional –4 penalty to his Armor Class. A pinned creature is limited in the actions that it can take. A pinned creature can always 
            attempt to free itself, usually through a combat maneuver check or Escape Artist check. A pinned creature can take verbal and mental actions, but 
            cannot cast any spells that require a somatic or material component. A pinned character who attempts to cast a spell or use a spell-like ability must 
            make a concentration check (DC 10 + grappler's CMB + spell level) or lose the spell. Pinned is a more severe version of grappled, and their effects do 
            not stack.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="ac" value="-4" />
        <mod type="dex_ac" value="0" />
        <mod type="actions" value="standard" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Shakened">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; -2 on attack rolls, saving throws, skill checks and ability checks<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A shaken character takes a –2 penalty on attack rolls, saving throws, skill checks, and ability checks. Shaken is a less severe state of fear than 
            frightened or panicked.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="hit" value="-2" />
        <mod type="saves" value="-2" />
        <mod type="skill_checks" value="-2" />
        <mod type="ability_checks" value="-2" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Sickened">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; -2 on attack rolls, weapon damage rolls, saving throws, skill checks and ability checks<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            The character takes a –2 penalty on all attack rolls, weapon damage rolls, saving throws, skill checks, and ability checks.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="damage" value="-2" />
        <mod type="hit" value="-2" />
        <mod type="saves" value="-2" />
        <mod type="skill_checks" value="-2" />
        <mod type="ability_checks" value="-2" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Staggered">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Single move or standard action<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A staggered creature may take a single move action or standard action each round (but not both, nor can he take full-round actions). A staggered 
            creature can still take free, swift and immediate actions. A creature with nonlethal damage exactly equal to its current hit points gains the 
            staggered condition.
        </long_description>
        <mod type="actions" value="single" />
    </condition>
    <condition
        name="Stunned">
        <short_description>
<![CDATA[
    	    &#8226; Drop everything held<br/>
    	    &#8226; Cannot take actions<br/>
    	    &#8226; -2 to AC<br/>
    	    &#8226; No Dex bonus to AC<br/>
		]]>
        </short_description>

        <long_description>
            A stunned creature drops everything held, can't take actions, takes a –2 penalty to AC, and loses its Dexterity bonus to AC (if any).
        </long_description>
        <mod type="actions" value="none" />
        <mod type="dex_ac" value="0" />
        <mod type="ac" value="-2" />
    </condition>

</item>